Guide to the John McClelland Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John McClelland papers
1860-1961
SC0255
McClelland, John, 1889-1961.
1.25 Linear feet
Correspondence between John McClelland and his former student, Philip Sheridan, spanning the years from Sheridan's graduation from Stanford (M.A. English) to McClelland's death in 1961; an extensive memorial volume regarding McClelland's life work, assembled by Sheridan; letters from McClelland to his former student Phyllis Kerr Yowell and her husband Robert Yowell, 1950-60; a scrapbook of clippings and illustrations on art and literature kept by McClelland; letters to his mother while serving in the armed forces during World War I, 1918-1919; and photographs, ca. 1860-1960. Letters to the Yowells discuss his teaching duties, literature, his reading, his life in retirement, and his cat. Also included in the papers are several letters to the Yowells from other academic friends, including one written from the Hemingway estate in Cuba; and letters to McClelland from J.P. Strachey and Dorothy Bussy, 1951, concerning Bussy's book OLIVIA.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Philip Sheridan, 1981, and Phyllis Yowell, 1993.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of English at Stanford (1925-1954; emeritus, 1955-1961).
Description of the Collection
Correspondence between John McClelland and his former student, Philip Sheridan, spanning the years from Sheridan's graduation from Stanford (M.A. English) to McClelland's death in 1961; an extensive memorial volume regarding McClelland's life work, assembled by Sheridan; letters from McClelland to his former student Phyllis Kerr Yowell and her husband Robert Yowell, 1950-60; a scrapbook of clippings and illustrations on art and literature kept by McClelland; letters to his mother while serving in the armed forces during World War I, 1918-1919; and photographs, ca. 1860-1960. Letters to the Yowells discuss his teaching duties, literature, his reading, his life in retirement, and his cat. Also included in the papers are several letters to the Yowells from other academic friends, including one written from the Hemingway estate in Cuba; and letters to McClelland from J.P. Strachey and Dorothy Bussy, 1951, concerning Bussy's book OLIVIA.
Access Terms
Bussy, Dorothy.; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; McClelland, John, 1889-1961.; Sheridan, Philip.; Stanford University. Department of English. Faculty.; Photoprints.; World War, 1914-1918.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Letters between Sheridan and McClelland
    - Letters, John McClelland to Philip Sheridan, 1944-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters, Philip Sheridan to John McClelland, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters, Philip Sheridan to John McClelland, 1945-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters between Sheridan and McClelland, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorial to John McClelland
    - "The Paw Under the Door," by Philip Sheridan, I. "Animals", Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - II. "People. A Crowd of Porcupines," III. "Pictures. You Remember the Pictures", Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - IV. "Books. The Spot of Blue Color", Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - V. "Books. None of Your Damned Punctilio," VI. "Books. The People on Stupidity Street", Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - VII. "Books. Like a Pasturing Cow," VIII. "Some Observations. The Genial Amusement of Passers By", Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, photographs, and other papers
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Letters, McClelland to Robert and Phyllis Yowell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Scrapbook, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letters from others to the Yowells, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous items, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1918 Mar-Jul (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1918 Aug (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1918 Sep (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1918 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1919 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Letters by Ted McClelland to Jack and Mrs. McClelland, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - French postcards and clipping, 1918, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letters re: book OLIVIA from J.P. Strachey and Dorothy Bussy (author), 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - OLIVIA, Hogarth Press, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 12)